North Africa, 1941.
Chaos in the middle of a breathtaking
landscape.
The desert on the border of Libya and
Egypt is like a film set. It's the scene
of a major and little known
confrontation of [music] the Second
World War, the Desert War.
Drunk with glory, Mussolini has
recklessly set out to conquer Egypt.
Fearing humiliation, Hitler has sent the
Africa Corps to his rescue.
At its head is Erwin Rommel,
a legendary general devoured by
ambition.
In defiance of the orders of the Führer,
who's focused on the Russian front,
Rommel challenges the British Empire in
Egypt.
And that's an intolerable affront to
Churchill.
Since 1940, Britain has been suffering
defeat after defeat.
In North Africa, victory is imperative,
whatever the cost.
So, Churchill has deployed considerable
forces there under the hitherto unknown
General Montgomery.
Here in these sands, he hopes the Reich
will finally bite the dust.
It's a huge endeavor.
The desert is a hell on earth.
It consumes bodies, burns souls, and
ruthlessly destroys machines.
Here in this furnace, can Montgomery
inflict a historic defeat on Rommel, the
Desert Fox, one that will change the
course of the war?
In these sands, will victory at last
choose their side?
>> [cheering]
[cheering]
>> It all begins with a big gamble by a
little dictator who dreams of greatness.
Benito Mussolini.
He proclaims that Italy must break the
bars of her Mediterranean prison.
Il Duce wants to restore the splendors
of the Roman Empire.
He dreams of controlling the
Mediterranean Sea and expanding his
empire into Africa.
Mussolini has inherited an empire whose
modesty is for him a sore point.
In the east, [music] it only controls
Somalia, Ethiopia, and Eritrea.
In the north, Libya was conquered at the
turn of the century by iron and blood.
Italy's victory was gained only by means
of multiple massacres and atrocities.
In the summer of 1940, the surprise
defeat of France turns the tables on the
war. It's a chance that Il Duce doesn't
intend to pass up on.
He wants to see the old colonial powers
that dominate Africa driven out.
Italy's time has come.
>> From Libya, he orders his troops to
enter Egypt, which is controlled by the
British.
A force of 80,000 men advances about 60
miles into Egyptian territory, where it
comes to a halt.
The Italian generals are hesitant.
They reckon their army is under-equipped
and not ready for such an adventure.
"It's my impression that our
preparations for war are a complete
mess," says one captain.
"The soldiers haven't been properly
trained. Some of them haven't even been
taught to shoot."
Winston Churchill doesn't want to let go
of Egypt at any price.
Ever since France surrendered, the Reich
has been extending [music] its grip on
Europe.
For the British Prime Minister, another
defeat would be unacceptable.
Especially since the Luftwaffe is
relentlessly pounding England.
Churchill knows that Britain's salvation
depends more than ever on the resources
of its empire.
And on the precious Suez Canal.
It's a vital artery for transporting raw
materials from Asia and Australia.
For Churchill, it's a very serious
situation.
But wouldn't the Italian attack be an
opportunity to play a dirty trick on
Hitler?
A crushing defeat of Italy in North
Africa would deprive the Führer of his
faithful ally. A triumph that would
perhaps offer a miracle solution to
defeating the Reich.
Unlike Mussolini, Churchill has a huge
empire at his back, the largest on the
planet.
He decides to tap into this reservoir to
defend Egypt.
During the autumn of 1940, thousands of
Australian, New Zealand, and South
African soldiers pour into Cairo.
The support is all the more precious
since the morale of the British soldiers
is low after the route they lived
through in Europe during the summer.
One British soldier, Reginald Crimp, is
27 years old. Just like so many of his
cohorts, this young father, who works in
a bank in London, isn't keen to fight in
the desert sands.
"Never has my home seemed so far away.
Outside of its central and cosmopolitan
district, Cairo is dirty and
dilapidated. [music]
The front is still a long way off, and
most of us are anxiously imagining the
journey that will take us there."
Two months after the Italian offensive,
the British counterattack.
To their great surprise, it's like a
stroll in the park.
The Italians in Libya are disorganized
and on the retreat.
The British even take Tobruk, a highly
strategic prize in this desert [music]
region.
It's the only port on the coast between
Egypt and Tripoli capable of harboring
the large ships that can carry
reinforcements and supplies to continue
the war.
In a matter of just a few weeks,
Commonwealth troops have won an outright
victory.
They've taken Eastern Libya from
Mussolini.
>> [cheering]
>> Worse, the Libyans are turning their
backs on him.
Il Duce thought he'd be bringing
civilization to these barbarians, but
the Muslim population now welcomes its
liberators.
It hasn't forgotten the 100,000 deaths
the Italian conquest was responsible
for, nor the race laws inspired by
apartheid that the fascist leader
imposed on them a few years earlier.
Churchill skillfully offers the Arabs of
Libya a deal.
In exchange for their loyalty to the
British forces, he promises them
independence once victory is achieved.
It's a good way to loosen the grip of
Rome.
40,000 Libyans agree to fight for
London.
Il Duce was yearning for glory, but now
reaps nothing but shameful defeat.
He leaves 130,000
prisoners behind on the battlefield.
Mussolini wanted to impose his rule in
Africa. Now he's calling for help.
By the beginning of 1941, Hitler has
turned his gaze to the east.
Along with his generals, the master of
all Europe is devoting himself to his
great project, Operation Barbarossa, the
conquest of the Soviet Union.
In his eyes, his victory will be sealed
out there on the Russian steppes.
Mussolini, on the other hand, has no
more cards to play. He has no choice but
to rely on his ally if he wants to avoid
losing Libya.
For two long days, Il Duce listens
mortified to lessons on strategy from
Hitler and his generals.
They're all pointing the finger at the
Italian operations, saying they're
unprepared.
Hitler has lost interest in North
Africa,
but he decides to help his ally.
His motives for helping are purely
political, says one general. He fears
that Mussolini will change sides if he's
not supported by Germany.
>> [snorts]
>> But, any German intervention will be on
the Führer's terms.
It must not under any circumstances
disrupt Barbarossa, which is expected to
be launched in just a few months.
The Führer sends only a small
expeditionary force to Mussolini's
rescue.
The Africa Corps has only 45,000 men and
250 tanks.
It lands in Tripoli, the capital of the
Italian colony.
Its mission is a limited one, to help
the Italians recapture Eastern Libya and
to protect it from a British onslaught.
The Führer gives command of the
operation to his favorite general,
Erwin Rommel.
This young officer, 49 years old, has
dazzled him with his spectacular
victories during the French campaign.
Officially Rommel is now under Italian
command.
But he's devoured by ambition and
refuses [music] to play second fiddle.
Rommel's not one of the old school of
German officers.
He's a maverick and he has dreams of
covering himself with glory in Africa.
A few weeks after his arrival, without
waiting for the Italians, he goes on the
attack.
His intentions are clear.
"My first objective," he says, "is to
recapture eastern Libya. My second is
Egypt and the Suez Canal."
It's an extravagant plan.
From the land of the pharaohs, he can
head for Baku in the Caucasus and get
his hands on the oil resources the Reich
so sorely lacks.
Then he can rendezvous with the
Wehrmacht troops to strike at Russia.
It's pure megalomania and far beyond
anything his leaders are expecting of
him.
But his troops are all for it.
For the Africa Corps is made up of elite
soldiers, all volunteers and committed
to the cause of the Reich.
"For us, Africa's a great adventure.
The oases, the camels, the veiled
beauties, they're all a fascinating
experience.
We're here to serve the fatherland under
General Rommel."
>> Rommel's sudden offensive comes as a
shock to the British.
The Germans aren't the same thing as the
Italians at all.
Faced with such a formidable adversary,
the worrying weaknesses of the British
Army start to emerge.
A biologist in civilian life,
27-year-old James Graham is a doctor in
the British Army.
He's horrified to see the extent of the
devastation [music] suffered by his
unit.
It's a blitz.
We've been devoured.
The whole area is covered with [music]
the smoldering remains of burned
vehicles and scattered bodies.
My job is to alleviate suffering and
save lives.
There's not much room for feelings.
They're burying their brothers in arms
right where they fell, if the enemy lets
them.
Seeing that the British are retreating,
Rommel decides to advance towards Egypt,
heading deeper into the desert.
He's well aware that he's now disobeying
orders. To his wife, Lucie, he
confesses,
"My darling Lucie,
we're attacking with remarkable success.
I've taken the risk of moving forward
despite all previous orders and
instructions in order to seize this
great opportunity."
Rommel has only one thing on his mind,
to seize Tobruk.
That's the price of glory.
The port is essential for him [music] to
transport his supplies and advance into
Egypt.
The British sense danger. They decide to
be cautious and abandon all the
territories they conquered in Libya, but
they barricade themselves in Tobruk.
Churchill orders his troops to hold on
to the port by all means.
That means supplies for 25,000 men by
sea.
On the front line, life's hard when
you're under siege. The men shelter from
the bombing in flea-infested holes.
Like rats, as the German radio
propaganda is always saying.
So, they start calling themselves the
Tobruk rats.
Harry Sutherland and his comrades
[music] in the Australian Brigade are
subjected to daily raids.
As soon as the planes arrive, we're
warned by the sirens.
We're next to the food depot, so we're
particularly targeted.
We talk to each other and help each
other because the constant tension can
really break your nerve.
They usually climb very high above us,
then swoop down very close to the
ground.
That's the scariest moment.
For the moment, Tobruk's still holding
on.
>> But Rommel is going for it.
He spends his days visiting his units
scattered around Tobruk and on the
Egyptian border.
He wants to see the battles from the
front lines
and tirelessly keeps ordering his men to
break through
whatever the cost.
Lieutenant Robert Witzke is a
professional soldier. He's 28 years old
and fighting on the front line.
He writes to his wife,
"Dear Inga,
every day there are attacks
and it will go on until one day Tobruk
is taken.
The English are just shooting wildly.
Every day we wonder which of our
comrades are still alive.
Many are dead, but many more are
injured.
Inga,
keep me in your thoughts."
150,000 Italian soldiers are fighting
alongside the Africa Corps,
an overwhelming number.
Rommel doesn't think much of their
military qualities and ignores the
opinions of their officers, whom he
openly despises.
But Il Duce's men don't lack courage.
Their weapons, though, are worn out and
not much use in battle.
Their generals' futile and costly
offensives are beginning to undermine
the men's confidence.
"Rommel has far too many ideas,
complains one brigade chief.
He gives an order and a few minutes
later he'll be thinking of something
else.
It's terrible fighting under Rommel,
disastrous.
After a 15-day siege, Rommel has
consumed an astronomical amount of
ammunition.
And the fuel's running out.
It doesn't matter.
To a battalion of machine guns, he
declares,
"We'll be in Cairo in 8 days. Spread the
word."
Obsessed with the idea of becoming a
legend, Rommel has neglected [music] a
crucial element of his war, fuel and
supplies.
But delivering the 4,000 tons of daily
supplies [music] that his relentless
attacks require is a daunting task.
Because the Axis supply lines are long
and dangerous.
In the Mediterranean, the British are
tracking down Italian cargo ships trying
to reach Tripoli, the only port
controlled by the Africa Corps.
All the same,
80% of supplies are still getting
through.
Petrol,
water,
food, ammunition.
Every day, once unloaded, the supplies
have to reach the front.
It's quite a challenge.
It takes 14 days to travel the 750 miles
from Tripoli to the front.
It's a real trial for the men.
Ironically,
the trucks consume half of the petrol
they carry.
>> Rommel's impatient with all this
logistical stuff. He exhausts his troops
and fails to take Tobruk.
His blindness costs the lives of 53
officers
and 1,200 men.
The head of the Africa Corps is severely
criticized in a report of the General
Staff.
The situation in North Africa is most
unsatisfactory.
Rommel is not up to the task.
Far from base and difficult to refuel,
the Africa Corps is dangerously exposed.
But Rommel's not willing to admit the
least error.
He blames his subordinates.
Some get the sack.
The message is clear. His men will have
to hold out, no matter how hard it gets.
The Khamsin, the burning wind that can
blow for long days at a time, heralds
the beginning of the hot season.
And the men face a formidable new enemy,
the desert,
and its scorching sun.
From May to October, it's impossible to
fight between 11:00 a.m. and 6:00 p.m.
Lieutenant Witzig has survived the hell
of Tobruk, and now he's knocked out by
the sun.
He confides to his wife,
"Hot is not the word.
For the past 10 days, it's been 130 140°
in the sun.
If they don't get us out of here, it'll
drive us all mad."
"Inga,
have you been for a swim yet?
I'd love to go swimming with you.
"The biggest problem is water." another
soldier laments.
"Drinking, always drinking. It's the
purpose of life in the desert."
"And water's difficult to transport, so
it's rationed."
"Inga, we're pigs.
Can you imagine washing only twice in 6
weeks?"
The soldiers are also confronted with
the scourge of the desert,
the flies.
Shortly after sunrise, they arrive in
their hordes.
They'll cover your arms, your face.
They'll get in your nose, your eyes.
They'll suck up your sweat, the only
moisture available in these arid lands.
You can't get away from them.
And there's no comfort in the food.
It's not good enough in both quality and
quantity.
They all try to survive by buying from
the Bedouins. And that may improve
Robert Witzke's daily life, but mainly
it confirms his racist stereotypes.
"We get eggs from the Arabs.
Those dogs, they're so wily they ask a
fortune for an egg.
We all reckon they're spies.
One look at these filthy animals and all
you can say is we have to get rid of
this scum."
>> Opposite in the British units camped on
the Egyptian border,
the pangs of hunger may not be so keen.
It's the depression that's torturing
them.
Private Reginald Crimp has been trapped
in the desert for 8 months now.
There's nothing there to distract him.
Overwhelmed with boredom, he writes in
his diary,
"The desert's everywhere. It drains your
spirit.
There's nothing here to look at, nothing
to listen to.
Every day it's the same old thing.
The only thing that keeps us holding on
is thoughts of home."
The British capital still bears the
scars of Hitler's bombings of the
previous year.
But thanks to the stubborn resistance of
an entire people, the Führer has failed
to break England.
But today, Churchill is exasperated
because in Africa [music] everything
suggests that his worn-out troops are
incapable of beating Rommel.
Criticized for his conduct of the war,
the Prime Minister tries to justify
himself before the British Parliament.
"We have a very daring and skillful
opponent against us [music] and may I
say, a great general."
But praising Rommel doesn't go far
towards explaining the serious setbacks
of the British Army.
What Churchill really needs is some
victories.
During the autumn of 1941, he sends
major reinforcements called up once
again from the Empire as well as Allied
forces.
From now on, North Africa has become a
major theater of war.
Indians, Africans, Poles, Greeks,
Czechs, over 150,000 men come to swell
the British ranks.
On this tower of Babel are also the free
French.
Responding to the call of General de
Gaulle, they will carry on the fight to
restore France's honor.
Churchill is taking [music] a gamble
that in the sands of Africa he can make
Hitler commit his first misstep.
And maybe change the course of the war.
The Führer is worried. At the end of
1941, the news from Africa is not good.
Rommel is outnumbered and in retreat.
Hitler's feeling trapped by the British
bulldog at the very moment he should
have a free hand.
Nearly 2,000 mi from the burning sands
of Africa, Operation Barbarossa is
entering a decisive phase.
At temperatures of minus 30° C,
the Wehrmacht are trying to take Moscow.
While the Eastern Front is keeping all
his forces busy,
Hitler nevertheless decides [music] to
send reinforcements to his protégé. He
can't afford to lose North Africa.
>> Rommel hasn't given up on his fantasies.
On the contrary.
The reinforcements Hitler sends him at
the beginning of 1942 are meager.
Barely enough to solve his logistical
problems.
But still just enough to let him dream
of a new raid on Cairo.
Once again, without even warning Rome or
Berlin, Rommel resumes his mad dash.
Energized now, he writes to his wife,
"My dear Lucie,
I have several plans in mind that I
would never dare to talk to my officers
about at the moment, or they might think
I was going crazy.
You know me.
It's in the wee small hours that my best
plans come to me."
For 6 months, Rommel fights a fierce
battle with British forces that are
clearly superior in number.
He must win, and fast, if he's not to be
beaten.
So, he comes up with a risky maneuver to
at the same time seize Tobruk and wipe
out his enemy.
"If he fails, he risks losing all of
Africa," writes one of his lieutenants.
In May 1942, he gives the order to his
crack units to bypass the British line
of defense.
His objective [music] is to surround
them, destroy them, and swoop onto
Tobruk.
But, in a remote spot, he comes across
an unexpected obstacle, Bir Hakeim.
It's a position held by the Free French
under General Koenig.
Just a handful of
3,600 men, 1,000 legionnaires, and a
majority of soldiers from the French
Empire.
African, Moroccan, [music] and Tahitian
gunners.
Faced with Rommel, they all know it's a
lost cause.
But Koenig asks them to hold steady.
"I've spoken with Rommel," he tells
them.
"He says if we don't turn ourselves in,
[music] he'll make mincemeat of us.
I told him to go to hell.
Good luck to you all."
Panzers and Stukas unleash a deluge of
fire on the French positions.
Susan Travers is the only woman [music]
present at Bir Hakeim.
She's General Koenig's driver, and she
insists [music] on staying with her
British comrades until the end.
"In this place that God has forgotten,
it is the howl of sirens that terrifies
me the most.
The exploding bombs burn and disfigure
everyone around me.
The dead are no longer picked up,
[music] and the wounded remain
unattended.
Rommel predicted he would crush [music]
us in a quarter of an hour. We've been
resisting him for 2 weeks."
2,600 survivors, running out of
ammunition, managed to leave their
position after a heroic resistance that
[music] has blocked Rommel for 14 days.
Susan, too, has survived. [music]
"This is a moment of great glory for the
Free French," she declares. "We have
restored the honor of the nation."
This is the feat of arms that de Gaulle
has been waiting for [music] to finally
obtain the recognition of the allies.
The British hail the achievement.
Thanks to the precious hours gained by
the Free French, their forces in the
midst of disaster have avoided being
surrounded.
They withdraw behind the Egyptian
border, but for the second time abandon
the east of Libya to the enemy.
At great risk, Rommel has triumphed.
He's taken the port of Tobruk.
Robert Witzke plays a leading role in
this victory.
"Our battalion," he proclaims, "once
again has the honor of leading the way.
Jesus Christ, Tobruk is ours. It's still
hard to believe."
Two days after his triumph, Robert
Witzke is severely injured.
He is evacuated to Germany.
German war reporters have followed
Rommel's every step during the last
phase of the battle.
Images like these trumpet his
achievement all over the world.
The legend is forged of the desert fox.
But while the cameras are all focused on
Rommel,
they're careful not to film the vendetta
of the Italian settlers.
The Arab people chose the British camp.
They pay the price.
The looting and murders are multiplying.
One Italian settler rejoices.
No sooner had the English fled than any
Arab we found got a bullet in the head
or a grenade in the guts.
Our soldiers are here now finishing the
job.
There's violence too against Libya's
30,000 Jews, whether they supported the
British or not.
Fascist race laws have previously
[music] been applied only mildly to
these Italian citizens.
But with the military setbacks, there's
been a radicalization of the fascist
regime.
Il Duce decides to intern all the Jews
in the region.
Entire [music] families are being
arrested, loaded into trucks, and dumped
in concentration camps set up on the
edge of the desert.
The worst of these death camps is in
Giado, 150 mi south of Tripoli.
About 3,000 people will be held there.
A quarter of them will die of
undernourishment and ill treatment.
Churchill hears of the disaster of
Tobruk while meeting with Franklin
Roosevelt at the White House.
It's one of the most violent blows I
remember receiving.
Learning the news in the presence of
one's great ally adds insult to injury.
Defeat is one thing.
Dishonor is quite another.
The latest polls are damning. Half the
British don't [music] trust him anymore.
Just like Mussolini with Hitler,
Churchill must gain the support of his
[music] ally.
His political survival depends on it.
Six months earlier, the US president
plunged America into the World War.
All his attention now directed to the
Pacific area where his troops are
fighting Japan.
Whenever they meet, Churchill harasses
him to land on the African coast and
help to crush Rommel.
He argues that North Africa would offer
a terrific springboard to then attack
Hitler in Europe.
The whole plan appalls the American
generals.
They believe that to defeat Germany, you
have to strike at its heart in Europe.
So they're planning a landing on the
French coast that could be ready in
barely a year's time.
But the bulldog is a good politician.
To convince his host, he insists that it
would be harmful to remain inactive for
a year with public opinion in the US
impatient and hungry for victories.
It's an attractive argument to the
American president.
After all, it's true. He has elections
coming up soon.
The Desert Fox ignores all this
scheming.
At the end of June 1942, he decides to
advance into Egypt with Hitler's
blessing this time.
The Führer now believes the conquest of
Egypt will be an historic turning point
and a means of bringing about the fall
of the British Empire.
Rommel is confident of victory in less
than 2 weeks.
So, he's planning his holidays.
He writes to his wife,
"My very dear Lucie, we're on the march
to our final objective.
We'll be able to go to Italy in July.
Get the passports ready."
El Alamein is a small railway station on
the Egyptian coast.
It's here that the British generals
decide to fight the last battle.
They've chosen this position so as not
to be surrounded again by the Desert
Fox.
It has impossible obstacles on every
side.
The sea to the north,
a vast area of soft sand to the south.
However, from the very first shots,
things go very wrong for His Majesty's
troops.
Over the past year, they've suffered
defeat after defeat despite their
superior numbers.
The inept strategies of their leaders
and their fear of Rommel have undermined
their resolve.
A lot of them are wondering what the
point is of fighting an invincible
enemy.
In his field hospital, Dr. James Graham
is seeing a flood of soldiers, all
broken men unable to continue the fight.
He knows that some would rather mutilate
themselves than go back to the front.
One of the most radical methods used by
the men of my regiment is to break a
rifle cartridge and swallow the
explosive, a poison for the liver.
After a few weeks in the hospital,
there's a chance you might get a
non-combatant job.
By the summer of 1942, the collapse of
morale has reached alarming proportions.
The head of the British forces sees his
men surrendering in droves to the enemy.
Such defeatism is unacceptable. He calls
for the reintroduction of the death
penalty for deserters.
For a month now, Winston Churchill has
watched the agonies of his troops in El
Alamein.
Devoured by anxiety, he rushes to Cairo.
The German offensive is for the moment
contained, but he ruthlessly dismisses
his general, whom he considers
responsible for the route.
Churchill admires Rommel's tactical
acumen. He's come to the conclusion that
the key to success is to find the right
leader.
After much hesitation, he opts for
General Bernard Montgomery.
He's the son of a pastor who didn't
spare the rod and is as dry in
appearance as he is of heart.
Churchill finds him proud,
but he chooses Montgomery because to his
eyes, he has a precious quality,
an immense self-confidence that he is
able to communicate to those around him.
The doctor, James Graham, is attached to
Montgomery's headquarters.
He sees him struggling to cure the
ailments that plague his men.
Montgomery is out there every day.
He makes a point of going around all the
units to introduce himself to the
soldiers. No commander has ever done
that before.
The new chief's message to his men is
simple but firm.
The defense of Egypt is based here at El
Alamein.
We shall hold on and fight here.
There will be no further retreat.
Clearly under him, they'll not give an
inch of ground to Rommel.
As James Graham says,
the men immediately understood that this
was a man determined to succeed, so we
had a better chance of ending this war.
That was enough to earn our loyalty.
To constantly remind himself of the
challenge he faces, Montgomery has
pinned up a photo of Rommel in his
command car.
Strategically, he's the complete
opposite of the Desert Fox.
He prefers to meticulously prepare his
plans.
I spend the day inspecting the terrain.
All the intelligence leads me to believe
that Rommel will attack towards the end
of the month.
I have to correctly plan how to beat
him.
Montgomery has got it right.
A month after he takes command, his
opponent goes back on the offensive.
The new British strategist feels ready.
Rather than gamble on an unlikely
decisive battle, Montgomery decides to
wear his opponent out.
He is after all very much better
equipped.
My plan is to contain the enemy's tanks
while we proceed to methodically destroy
his forces at the rear to cut him off
from his supplies.
Montgomery targets Rommel's weak point,
his petrol supply convoys.
Theo Elmauck drives a supply truck for
the Africa Corps.
He suffers another air attack that will
mark him for the rest of his life.
The attack lasted only a few moments.
I was pretty knocked about. Then I was
overwhelmed by this incredible panic.
Now it really is war in all its cruelty,
in all its horror.
At El Alamein, fear changes sides.
Montgomery writes to a friend.
My first confrontation with Rommel was
really very interesting.
I feel like I won the first set,
although it was his service.
Next time, it'll be me to serve.
Rommel remains confident.
Even flies to Europe to treat a bad case
of flu.
His journey turns into a lap of triumph.
In front of the cameras, Hitler promotes
him.
Tobruk is well worth a marshal's staff.
Bathing in glory, the desert fox is
cheered at a rally in his honor at the
Berlin Sports Palace.
He tells the adoring crowd,
We have the gates of Egypt within reach.
>> [cheering]
>> But he speaks too soon.
At El Alamein, his triumph will turn
into a disaster.
Rommel returns in panic to take back
command at the end of October.
Montgomery's wear and tear strategy
[music] has paid off.
He's only got a few days fuel left.
Two days after his return, the Desert
Fox [music] is finally done for.
British intelligence intercepts a German
message indicating the imminent arrival
of two Italian tankers in the port of
Tobruk.
But as they prepare to drop anchor,
Royal Air Force bombers sink them both.
So with no fuel left, there's nothing
more Rommel can do.
At El Alamein, the Desert Fox has
suffered a terrible defeat.
He knows that it will ruin his Führer's
ambitions in Africa.
It's a broken man who writes to his
wife.
God only knows if I will survive this
defeat.
If I never return, I want from the
bottom of my heart to thank you and our
son for all the love and happiness you
have brought me.
>> The victory at El Alamein marks a
turning point in the Second World War.
Rommel's army has been defeated.
The British Prime Minister doesn't hide
his pleasure.
Ah, this is not the end.
Uh it is not even the beginning
of the end.
Uh but it is perhaps the end of the
beginning.
Churchill's gloating.
He knows that now the Reich's days in
Africa are numbered.
The bulldog's stubbornness has paid off.
Despite opposition from his generals,
Roosevelt has given in to him.
Five days after the triumph of El
Alamein, American troops land in North
Africa. On the beaches of Morocco and
Algeria, there are two French colonies.
The US president wants to win the
midterm elections. He has promised his
public an easy victory over on the
African continent.
Initially scheduled to last 4 weeks,
Operation Torch, the epilogue to the
desert war, will in fact last for 7 long
months.
The English and American forces and
Montgomery's army have planned to meet
up in Tunisia. It's their chosen
springboard to strike at Europe.
Hitler understands Churchill's visionary
strategy. It's about time.
Now he wants to block [music] the way to
the Allies, whatever the price.
He sends more and more reinforcements
due
and even transfers some Luftwaffe
bombers from the Russian front.
The ferocity of the fighting dulls the
enthusiasm of the Americans, most of
them novices.
Paul Robinett commands an armored
regiment of the US Army.
His men engage in the first major
confrontation against the Wehrmacht in
February 1943 in Kasserine.
The commander looks on helplessly as his
troops are routed.
There's indescribable confusion and
signs of panic.
Our army is no more than a battered
force that's retreating in haste. Some
at the rear are saying we're not worthy
to fight.
But, this terrible baptism of fire has
hardened the GIs.
On the 28th of March 1943, they can at
last join up [music] with Montgomery's
troops.
The British and Americans now have
overwhelming superiority.
They launch their final offensive in the
center of Tunisia.
Three weeks later, the British enter
Tunis
and the Americans [music]
enter Bizerte.
The Axis troops, crammed into their
final refuge, surrender [music]
unconditionally.
The Allies take 275,000 [music]
prisoners, far more than the 90,000 men
taken at the fall of Stalingrad,
earning the battle the flattering
nickname of Tunisgrad.
These thousands of soldiers won't be
there to repel the allies [music] at the
Normandy landings.
And so ends the desert war.
The people celebrate their liberators.
The Allied victory may have rid Africa
of the brown plague of Nazism,
but it hasn't broken the chains of
colonialism.
The road to independence will still be a
long one.
The allies are now ready to engage in
the great confrontation in Western
Europe.
They have, like Montgomery, tamed modern
warfare.
A lesson hard learned by leaders and men
alike at the cost of terrible suffering.
Victory may have changed sides in the
sands of Africa, but it will take
another two long years for the Allied
flags to finally fly over Berlin.